Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Thomas Sutton Papers, 1965-1975 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Thomas Sutton papers 1965-1975 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company.
6.6 linear feet Extent: 4950 Items
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Thomas Sutton was an executive in charge of JWT's international operations during the 1960s-1970s. The Thomas Sutton Papers span the years 1965-1975 and document Sutton's career, especially his role in JWT's international expansion and the establishment of global advertising markets. The papers provide insight into JWT's international financial matters--budgets, salary structure, stock incentive plans and market shares--as well as personnel policies, client relations, product launches, television advertising projects and marketing research and strategies, seen from the perspective of Sutton's position as JWT chief executive for international operations. The papers also contain marketing plans, evaluations and reports for a number of JWT's international offices, that provide a detailed glimpse into JWT's operations within the respective countries' economic and socio-political contexts. The offices represented include Amsterdam, Bogotá, Brussels, Buenos Aires, Caracas, Ceylon, Copenhagen, Frankfurt, Johannesburg, Karachi, Lima, London, Mexico City, Milan, Paris, Rio de Janeiro, San Juan, Santiago, Sydney, Tokyo, Toronto, Vienna and Zürich. Key clients include the Honda Motor Company, Eastman Kodak Company, Ford Motor Company, the Hertz Corporation, IBM, Johnson & Johnson, Kellogg Company, Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company, Nestlé, Pan American World Airways, PepsiCo, Inc. and Unilever (Lever Brothers).
RL.00752
Language: Material in English, Spanish, Portuguese
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Sensitive personnel materials pertaining to individual employee matters are closed to non-JWT users for 75 years from the date of the file creation.
Fragile originals are closed to patron use. Consult Use Copies in files.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company Thomas Sutton Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1987.
Biographical Note
1923 Feb. 9 Born Thomas Schulhof, in Berlin (of Austrian Jewish descent, the Schulhof family relocated to England to escape the Nazis, and changed its name to Sutton during World War II)
1948 Received M.A. in Philosophy, Politics, and Economics from St. Peter’s College, Oxford University
1949 Research officer at British Market Research Bureau (BMRB), a subsidiary of J. Walter Thompson Co. (JWT) London
1951 Left JWT to work as Advertising and Market Research Manager for Pasolds Limited, a textile manufacturer
1952 Returned to JWT London, and sent to Frankfurt, Germany, as Managing Director; charged with reopening the JWT office in Germany which had ceased operations in 1934
1960 Returned to England to assume position of Managing Director, JWT London
1966 Executive Vice President, International
1966-1972 Executive Vice President at JWT New York, responsible for all 37 of JWT’s international operations
1970 International Advertising Man of the Year Award
1972 Stepped down from New York post to become General Manager for JWT Japan in Tokyo
1980 Executive Vice President, JWT's Asia-Pacific operations
1981 Dec. Executive Vice President, JWT Group
1983 Dec. 31 Retired as Executive Vice President of J. Walter Thompson Company and a member of its Board of Directors, and as Executive Vice President of JWT Group, Inc.
1994 Dec. 9 Died at the age of 71
Sutton received several honors during his lifetime. In Great Britain he served on the Council of Institute of Practictioners in Advertising and headed their Development Committee. He was also a Fellow of the Royal Historical Statistical Society and a fellow of the Institute of Statisticians. In the United States, Sutton was a member of the Advisory Board of International Business Program of Rutgers University.
Collection Overview
The Thomas Sutton Papers span the years 1965-1975 and document Sutton's career, especially his role in JWT's international expansion and the establishment of global advertising markets. The papers include correspondence, printed materials, business reports, advertising brochures, photographs, statistical documents, and pamphlets that provide insight into JWT's international financial matters--budgets, salary structure, stock incentive plans and market shares--as well as personnel policies, client relations, product launches, television advertising projects and marketing research and strategies, seen from the perspective of Sutton's position as JWT chief executive for international operations. The papers also contain marketing plans, evaluations and reports for a number of JWT's international offices, that provide a detailed glimpse into JWT's operations within the respective countries' economic and socio-political contexts. The offices represented herein include Amsterdam, Bogotá, Brussels, Buenos Aires, Caracas, Ceylon, Copenhagen, Frankfurt, Johannesburg, Karachi, Lima, London, Mexico City, Milan, Paris, Rio de Janeiro, San Juan, Santiago, Sydney, Tokyo, Toronto, Vienna and Zürich. Key clients include the Eastman Kodak Company; Ford Motor Company; the Hertz Corporation; Honda Motor Company; IBM; Johnson & Johnson; Kellogg Company; Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company; Nestlé; Pan American World Airways; PepsiCo, Inc.; and Unilever (Lever Brothers). While most of the files are in English, some of the documents are written in Spanish and Portuguese.
The collection is organized into three Series--the General Office Files Series; the Central and South American Office Files Series; and the Annual Marketing Plans and Reports Series.
The General Files Series contains correspondence, memoranda and periodical reports on JWT management and marketing, JWT's international offices and operations, as well as on other international advertising agencies. Topics include capital expenditures, fees and commissions, management salary and bonus policies, and stock incentive plans. The correspondence on international new business includes clients such as Hertz, Honda, and IBM. Arranged alphabetically.
The Central and South American Offices Files Series contains correspondence and reports on JWT budgets, market shares, profits, marketing research and product launches, as well as newsletters and some newspaper clippings pertaining to individual country offices of JWT throughout Latin America. The documents reflect the communication between JWT personnel and the dealings between JWT and its large international clients such as Ford, Johnson & Johnson, Kellogg's, Kodak, Lever, Liggett & Myers, Pan American World Airways, Pepsi-Cola, and Nestle, as well as prospective clients like Siemens and local clients in Central America and South America. The documents provide insights into JWT's operation in the expanding advertising markets of Central and South America. This series also includes assessments of the respective countries' economies, census data, and the competition in the advertising market. Moreover, it shows the increasing importance of television advertising in the Latin American market. Organized alphabetically.
Annual Marketing Plans and Reports Series contains status and planning reports from JWT's international operations. The documents assess the respective country's economy, politics, and the advertising and media market as a context for presenting a review of the JWT's offices' financial and organizational performance that includes billings, expenditures, and profits, salaries, personnel, specific clients, and the company's public relations in the respective past year. This analysis of strengths and weaknesses provides the bases for a discussion of the targets and objectives for the respective next year. Arranged alphabetically.
Restriction on access: Sensitive personnel materials pertaining to individual employee matters are closed to non-JWT users until 2043. Those items have been physically removed to Restricted Materials. Fragile original materials have been relocated to Removed Materials. Use Copies are available to patrons.
Additional information on JWT's international advertising operations may be found in the J. Walter Thompson Co. London Office Records, the J. Walter Thompson Co. Frankfurt Office Records, the Harry Clark Papers, the Arthur Stridsberg Papers, and the Shirley F. Woodell Papers. In addition, files relating to Thomas Sutton may be found in the Denis Lanigan Papers and the Peter Gilow Papers.
Subject Headings
Sutton, Thomas (Thomas Francis); J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson Company. Amsterdam Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Bogotá Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Brussels Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Buenos Aires Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Caracas Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Ceylon Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Copenhagen Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Frankfurt Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Johannesburg Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Karachi Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Lima Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. London Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Mexico City Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Milan Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. New York Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Paris Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Rio de Janeiro Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. San Juan Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Santiago (Chile); J. Walter Thompson Company. Sydney Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Tokyo Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Toronto Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Vienna Office; J. Walter Thompson Company. Zürich Office; Eastman Kodak Company; Ford Motor Company; Hertz Corporation; Honda Motor Company; International Business Machines Corporation; Johnson & Johnson; Kellogg Company; Liggett & Myers Tobacco Company; Pan American World Airways, Inc.; PepsiCo, Inc.; Nestlé; Unilever (Firm); Advertising agencies -- Argentina; Advertising agencies -- Australia; Advertising agencies -- Austria; Advertising agencies -- Belgium; Advertising agencies -- Brazil; Advertising agencies -- Canada; Advertising agencies -- Chile; Advertising agencies -- Colombia; Advertising agencies -- Denmark; Advertising agencies -- Employees; Advertising agencies -- Europe; Advertising agencies -- France; Advertising agencies -- Germany; Advertising agencies -- Great Britain; Advertising agencies -- Italy; Advertising agencies -- Japan; Advertising agencies -- Mexico; Advertising agencies -- Netherlands; Advertising agencies -- Pakistan; Advertising agencies -- Peru; Advertising agencies -- Puerto Rico; Advertising agencies -- South Africa; Advertising agencies -- Spain; Advertising agencies -- Switzerland; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Venezuela; Advertising -- History -- 20th century; Advertising -- Research; Marketing research; Television advertising; Photographs; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- General Office Files Series, 1966-1971, (2 boxes)
  Contains correspondence, memoranda and periodical reports on JWT management and marketing, JWT's international offices and operations, as well as on other international advertising agencies. Topics include capital expenditures, fees and commissions, management salary and bonus policies, and stock incentive plans. The correspondence on international new business includes clients such as Hertz, Honda, and IBM. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Capital Employment in JWT, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Correspondent agencies, 1968-1972, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - International Advertising Association, 1966, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Latin American seminar, 1970-1971, (6 folders) (Box 1)
  - Managers' Meeting III: People Management, 1970 (Box 1)
  - Memoranda
    - Commission structure, 1967-1972 (Box 1)
    - Management bonus program, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Remuneration of senior executives, 1969 (Box 1)
  - New business, 1969-72, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Public stock offering, 1969, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Statistical background, international operations, 1968 and 1969 (Box 2)
  - Stock incentive plans, 1969-1972, (2 folders) (Box 2)
- Central and South American Office Files Series, 1965-1969 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Contains correspondence and reports on JWT budgets, market shares, profits, marketing research and product launches, as well as newsletters and some newspaper clippings for JWT offices in Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Mexico and Peru, among others. The documents reflect the communication between JWT personnel and the dealings between JWT and its large international clients such as Ford, Johnson & Johnson, Kellogg's, Kodak, Lever, Liggett & Myers, Pan American World Airways, Pepsi-Cola, and Nestlé, as well as prospective clients like Siemens and local clients in Central America and South America. The documents provide insight into JWT's operation in the expanding advertising markets of Central and South America. This series also includes assessments of the respective countries' economies, census data, and the competition in the advertising market. Moreover, it shows the increasing importance of television advertising in the Latin American market. Arranged alphabetically. A few folders of general material are listed first under some office names.
  Restriction on access: Sensitive personnel materials pertaining to individual employee matters are closed to non-JWT users until 2043. Those items have been physically removed to Restricted Materials; a dummy folder, indicated by a title enclosed in brackets, has been substituted for the original material.
  - Argentina
    - Budget, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Clients, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Finance, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - New business, 1968 (Box 3)
    - [Personnel, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 3)
    - Regular reports, 1968 (Box 3)
    - [Salaries and profit sharing, 1967-1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 3)
  - Brazil
    - Budget, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - [Cavalcanti, Carlos, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 3)
    - Clients, 1967-1968 and undated, (3 folders) (Box 3)
    - Correspondence, 1968, (2 folders) (Box 3)
    - Medical/Pension plan, August 28, 1968 (Box 3)
    - New business, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Pepsi-Cola, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - [Personnel, 1968 and undated: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
    - Press clippings, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Regular reports, 1967, 1968 (Box 4)
    - [Salaries and profit sharing, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
    - Transfers
      - [Eaves, Elliott, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
      - [Gibson, Chuck, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
      - [Raiburn, Gerald, 1966, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
      - [Wallace, Robert, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
  - Chile
    - General, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Budget, 1967, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Clients, 1967, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1968 (Box 4)
    - New business, 1968 (Box 4)
    - [Personnel, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
    - Regular reports, 1968 (Box 4)
    - [Salaries and profit sharing, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
  - Colombia
    - General, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Mexico
    - General, 1968 and undated (Box 4)
    - Budget, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Clients, 1968 and undated (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1968 and undated (Box 4)
    - New business, 1968, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Space 1968 (Box 4)
    - [Personnel, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
    - Regular reports, 1968 (Box 4)
    - [Salaries, 1967, 1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 4)
  - Peru
    - Budget, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Clients, 1968 and undated (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1967-1968, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - New business, 1968 (Box 5)
    - [Personnel, 1967-1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 5)
    - Regular reports, 1968 (Box 5)
    - [Salaries and profit sharing, 1967-1968: Folder removed to Restricted Materials] (Box 5)
  - Multiple Accounts and Country Offices
    - General, 1967-1968 (Box 5)
    - Linten, Jose, television proposal, 1966-1967 (Box 5)
      Linten, a Spanish television executive, proposed the creation of the first Latin American television network.
    - Marketing, 1968 (Box 5)
- Annual Marketing Plans and Reports Series, 1966-1975 and undated, (6 boxes)
  Contains status and planning reports from JWT's international operations. The documents assess the respective country's economy, politics, and the advertising and media market as the context for then reviewing the individual JWT office's financial and organizational performance. These reviews include billings, expenditures, and profits, salaries, personnel, specific clients, and the company's public relations in the respective past year. This analysis of strengths and weaknesses then provides the basis for a discussion of the targets and objectives for the upcoming year. Also included for some countries are executive summaries of annual reports that offer a comparative overview of JWT's operations in larger geographical areas, such as Europe. Reports from JWT offices in countries where the company had only recently been established by the mid- or late 1960s, such as the Far East (like Pakistan), are often very short compared to the reports of more established offices in the larger countries of Europe, Scandinavia, or Latin America. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Canada
    - JWT Canada
      - Annual marketing report, 1967 Jan. 16 (Box 5)
  - Europe
    - JWT Amsterdam
      - Annual marketing plan, 1970-1973, (3 folders) (Box 5)
      - Marketing plan, 1969 (Box 5)
      - Marketing report, 1967-1968, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - JWT Brussels
      - Annual marketing plan, 1970-1971 (Box 5)
      - Annual marketing report, 1968 (Box 5)
      - Client costing report on financial managers' meeting, 1973 (Box 5)
      - JWT Brussels, circa 1975 (Box 5)
      - Long term policy and objectives, 1972 (Box 5)
      - Marketing plan, 1969, 1973 (Box 5)
    - JWT Europe
      - Executive summary of continental annual marketing reports, 1970 Nov. (Box 6)
    - JWT Frankfurt
      - Annual management assessment and objectives, 1975 (Box 6)
      - Annual marketing plan, 1968-1972, (4 folders) (Box 6)
      - Annual marketing report, 1967, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - Summary of the report on the office's business, 1973 Sept. 26 (Box 6)
    - JWT London
      - Annual marketing report, 1966-1970, (4 folders) (Box 6)
    - JWT Madrid
      - Annual marketing plan, 1969-1972, (3 folders) (Box 6)
      - Marketing plan, Emarbe S.A., 1972 Dec. (Box 6)
    - JWT Milan (JWT Italia)
      - 5-Year plan, 1975 Apr. (Box 7)
      - Annual account review, 1974 Mar. (Box 7)
      - Annual marketing plan for 1974, 1973 Dec. (Box 7)
      - Annual marketing report, 1967, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Marketing plan, 1968-1972, (4 folders) (Box 7)
      - Marketing plan, Emarbi S.r.l., 1972 Dec. (Box 7)
    - JWT Paris
      - Annual marketing plan, 1968-1970, (3 folders) (Box 7)
      - Annual marketing report, 1966-1967 (Box 7)
      - Executive summary of 1973 marketing plan, 1973 (Box 7)
    - JWT Scandinavia
      - Annual marketing report, Copenhagen, 1967 Nov. (Box 7)
      - Marketing plan for 1971, 1970 Nov. 2 (Box 7)
      - Scandinavia, 1967-1972, (2 folders) (Box 7)
      - Scandinavian marketing plan, circa 1973 (Box 7)
      - Second annual marketing plan, Copenhagen, 1968 Nov. (Box 7)
    - JWT Vienna
      - Annual management assessment/objectives, 1975 Jan. (Box 8)
      - Marketing plan, 1968, 1972 (Box 8)
    - JWT Zürich
      - Annual management assessment, 1975 Jan. (Box 8)
      - Annual marketing report, circa 1967 (Box 8)
      - Marketing plan, 1968-1972 (Box 8)
      - Marketing report, circa 1968 (Box 8)
  - Far East
    - JWT Ceylon
      - Annual marketing report, 1966-1967 (Box 8)
    - JWT Pakistan (Karachi)
      - Annual marketing report, circa 1967 (Box 8)
      - Review of annual marketing reports, 1968-1970 (Box 8)
  - Latin America and Caribbean
    - JWT Latin America
      - 1970 year-end closing/1971 revised reporting 1971 Jan. (Box 8)
      - 9 months operating results, 1971 Sept. 30 (Box 8)
      - Executive summary of Latin American annual marketing reports, 1972 Apr. (Box 8)
      - Financial review visit, 1971 Mar. 10-Apr. 20 (Box 8)
    - JWT Argentina (Buenos Aires)
      - Annual marketing plan, 1972 Dec. (Box 8)
      - Annual marketing report, 1965, 1968, (2 folders) (Box 8)
      - Argentina-Uruguay annual marketing report forecast, budget 1970, 1969 Oct. (Box 8)
      - Presentation to the Executive Committee, 1973 Apr. 2 (Box 8)
    - JWT Brazil (Rio de Janeiro)
      - Annual marketing report, 1967-1968, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Executive summary of marketing plans, circa 1973 (Box 9)
      - Marketing plan, 1973 Jan. (Box 9)
      - Review of annual marketing report, 1966 Dec. (Box 9)
    - JWT Chile (Santiago)
      - Annual marketing plan, 1967-1969, (3 folders) (Box 9)
      - Review of annual marketing report, circa 1966 (Box 9)
    - JWT Mexico
      - Annual marketing report, 1967-1972, (5 folders) (Box 9)
      - Financial review, presentation made to the JWT Board of Directors in New York, 1973 Feb. 14 (Box 9)
    - JWT Peru (Lima)
      - Annual management assessment-objectives, 1975 Jan. (Box 9)
      - Annual marketing plan, background aspects, review and preview, 1972 Dec. (Box 9)
      - Annual marketing report, 1966-1967, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Executive summary of annual marketing plan, 1971 Dec. (Box 9)
      - Review of annual marketing report, 1968-1969, (2 folders) (Box 9)
    - JWT Puerto Rico (San Juan)
      - Annual marketing plan, 1969-1970, (2 folders) (Box 9)
      - Annual marketing plan, JWT Caribbean, 1972 Dec. (Box 9)
      - Annual marketing report, JWT Caribbean, 1967-1969, (3 folders) (Box 9)
    - JWT Venezuela (Caracas)
      - Annual marketing plan, 1971 Nov. 1 (Box 9)
      - Annual marketing report, 1966-1970, 1973, (7 folders) (Box 9)
  - Pacific Area
    - JWT Australia
      - Annual marketing plan, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Annual marketing report, 1967 (Box 10)
      - Annual report, 1968-1971, (5 folders) (Box 10)
        Original of 1968 report located in Removed Materials, Box 11 (Use Copy available in folder)
      - Quarterly survey, Australia-New Zealand Limited, 1968 Oct. (Box 10)
    - JWT Japan
      - Annual marketing report, 1967-1969, (4 folders) (Box 10)
      - Marketing plan, appendix, 1973 Feb. (Box 10)
    - JWT Philippines
      - Annual marketing plan, 1973 (Box 10)
      - Annual marketing report, 1966-1970, (4 folders) (Box 10)
  - South Africa
    - JWT Johannesburg
      - Objectives and communications plan, 1977 Jan. (Box 10)
- Restricted Materials, 1966-1968, (1 box)
  Restriction on access: Sensitive personnel materials pertaining to individual employee matters are closed to non-JWT users until 2043.
  - Central and South American Offices Files Series, 1966-1968 and undated
    - Argentina, 1967-1968
      - Personnel, 1968 (Box 11)